DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宮飯》
I overslept!
我睡過頭了！
I can't hear his heartbeat.
聽不到他的心跳聲
Of course, you can't hear it from over his armor.
廢話，你隔著鎧甲當然聽不到啊
He finally managed to fall asleep a little while ago.
他不久前好不容易才睡著呢
Seems like the food poisoning symptoms are letting up as well.
看來他食物中毒的症狀似乎也緩和了
I see. So, I made a fuss over nothing.
什麼嘛，害人窮緊張
Let him sleep a little longer.
讓他再多睡一下吧
It seems he was delirious all throughout the night.
他好像痛苦呻吟了整整一個晚上
You know, here in this dungeon, even the number of monsters
話說這座迷宮居然 連入侵者會打倒的魔物數量
that are defeated by intruders are taken into account.
也都計算好了
Even when we defeat monsters,
就算我們打倒了魔物
we're only maintaining the balance of the ecosystem.
也只是在維持生態平衡
But if we let them be, the monsters will wander into towns.
但要是放著不管 魔物又會多到跑進城鎮
And the towns will hire adventurers to hunt the monsters.
傷透腦筋的城鎮會委託冒險者去討伐
It's designed so well.
設計得真周到
What are you talking about?
你在講什麼啊？
The design of the dungeon, of course.
當然是在講迷宮的設計啊
I studied it in school a long time ago.
我以前有在學校學過一點
But it was really tricky.
但內容有夠難的
Hey, look.
嘿，你看
That's Marcille from the graduate school, isn't it?
那是研究科的瑪露希爾同學對不對？
The most brilliant female student in the school's history!
她就是那個學校 有史以來最優秀的才女！
I heard she assisted a teacher on her very first day here.
聽說她入學當天就當了老師的助手
And I heard she's already on track to become the court mage.
她好像已經確定會擔任宮廷魔術師了
Wow, that's amazing!
是喔，好厲害！
I didn't start as a teacher's assistant until my fifth day of school,
我是直到入學第五天 才開始當老師的助手的
and as for becoming a court mage, it's just that my parent used to be one.
而且只是父母 以前當過宮廷魔術師而已啦
Today, I asked the teacher to let me join the class.
今天我請求老師 讓我來和大家一起聽課
I hope we can get along.
請各位多多指教囉
-Y-Yeah!
-好的！
Today, we will try a spirit breeding experiment.
我們今天要做小精靈的繁殖實驗
Everyone, take a jar each and go outside.
請各位同學各拿一個玻璃罐到外面
Prepare wooden planks with holes in them
在穿了洞的木板上
and place them inside a jar, sandwiching them between layers of soil.
蓋上一層土，並在罐中層層交疊
Create a barrier,
設下結界
fill the jar with magic,
在裡頭注滿魔力
and release the spirits into it.
讓小精靈滴到罐中
The tiny spirits live solely on the magic inside the jar.
少數的小精靈只靠罐裡的魔力生存
If the magic is too strong or too weak, they will die.
魔力太多或太少都會導致其喪命
Breeding spirits is considered the foundation of summoning magic.
飼育小精靈可以說是召喚術的基礎
Because its structure resembles that of a dungeon that houses monsters,
因為構造與魔物所棲息的迷宮相似
it's referred to as a "dungeonium."
也被稱為“迷宮元素”
When you're done, place your jar inside the darkroom.
做完的同學請將玻璃罐放進暗室裡
We'll check on them a week from now.
期待一週後的成果吧
Wow, your barrier is so pretty, Marcille!
天哪，瑪露希爾同學的 結界好漂亮喔！
Are you sure this is your first time?
這真的是你第一次做嗎？
But why are you studying summoning magic?
可是你為什麼要學召喚術呢？
It's not your main field of study, is it?
這應該不是你的專攻吧？
I'm researching how to create a safe dungeon.
我正在研究建造安全迷宮的方法
Right now, I'm focused on the ingredients of magic.
現在如果需要魔法的材料
For example,
比方說
the way we currently gather Mandrakes is quite dangerous.
像是曼德拉草 我們都得冒著危險去採取
But if I can design a safe dungeon
但如果能建造出無害的迷宮
and grow only beneficial monsters inside it,
並在裡面只飼養有益處的魔物
I believe I could contribute to society.
我想就能對世人做出貢獻
Wow.
是喔
That's so cool.
好像很不得了
Check out Marcille's barrier!
看看瑪露希爾同學的結界吧！
It's so beautiful!
真的美呆了！
I want to see it, too!
也讓我看一下！
Let me see!
借我看…
Watch out!
小心！
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
T-Thanks.
謝謝你
The soil has impurities mixed in,
土壤中混進了雜質
and there are many gaps in the barrier, causing the magic to weaken.
結界又全是空隙，魔力流失許多
At this rate, the spirits inside won't be able to survive for long.
那樣裡面的小精靈是活不久的
I hope your uniform didn't get dirty.
衣服沒有被她弄髒吧？
That girl is always covered in mud,
那女生總是把自己弄得渾身是泥
and she keeps skipping class, so she's always lagging behind.
又常曠課，成績總是吊車尾
Everyone, retrieve your jars
各位同學，拿出自己的罐子
and check how many spirits are still alive.
驗收一下裡面還有多少小精靈吧
Oh no, they're all dead!
不好了，全都死光了！
They're just barely alive.
我的勉強還活著
I bred a new spirit species!
我培育出了新品種的小精靈！
That's mold.
那是黴菌啦
If there are many spirits still alive, the fire will burn strongly.
如果罐子裡有越多小精靈活著 火就會燒得越旺盛
Yours are almost in the same condition as they were a week ago.
你的幾乎保持原本的狀態呢
Good work.
做得很好…
M-My jar!
我的罐子！
Your spirits have multiplied quite a lot.
你的小精靈繁殖得真多呀
What should I do?
該怎麼辦才好？
I'll take care of it.
我來處理
How did you manage to do that?
你究竟是怎麼做出那種狀態的？
I-I'm sorry.
對不起
There's this place that's always teeming with spirits,
我只是看某個地方有很多小精靈
and I thought that using it as a reference might work.
想說如果參考那邊的環境 或許就可以讓實驗成功
Teeming with spirits?
有很多小精靈？
Where is this place?
你是指哪裡？
U-Um...
這個嘛…
This jar likely has just as many spirits as you'd find in a dungeon.
罐子裡的小精靈 應該和迷宮裡的一樣多
This will make a splendid sample.
會是個優秀的樣本喔
It's inside a real dungeon.
就是真正的迷宮
This is where I sneak outside.
我是從這裡出去的
A hidden passage?
居然還有這種密道？
Are you always doing stuff like this?
你常常這樣偷偷進來嗎？
Yup!
是呀！
So, that's why you're lagging behind.
怪不得會是吊車尾
A grasshopper!
蚱蜢！
Raspberries!
木莓！
Don't eat something so mysterious!
不要亂吃些奇怪的東西！
Don't touch them, either! They could be poisonous and dangerous!
也不要亂碰！如果有毒就危險了！
T-They're not mysterious.
並不是什麼奇怪的東西啦
Grasshoppers and raspberries aren't poisonous, either.
蚱蜢和木莓都沒有毒
It's a real dungeon.
真的是迷宮耶
I've never seen one before.
我是第一次看到
There's stagnant magic here, and the air is still.
魔力停滯在這裡，空氣不流通
It's a naturally formed cave.
看來是自然形成的洞窟
Hey, it's dangerous!
等一下，很危險！
Don't worry.
別擔心
I come here often.
我很常來這裡
You'll be safe as long as you stay on the dry ground.
只要走在乾燥的地面就安全了
Wow.
好壯觀
Dungeons really are teeming with spirits.
原來迷宮裡到處都是小精靈啊
I took the soil and water from here and placed them inside my jar.
我在罐子裡加進了這裡的土和水
I see.
原來是這樣
What do you usually do when you come here?
你平時都來這裡做什麼？
I write letters and read books.
我會寫些信，或是看點書
So, this is totally the result of her slacking off.
所以這完全是她翹課的成果
Anyway, this place seems pretty safe.
總之這裡看來是沒有危險
Hold on.
等一下
If I cultivate this place and plant Mandrakes,
如果我在這裡耕一塊地，種曼德拉草
I'll be able to use the dungeon's magic safely.
就可以安全地利用迷宮的魔力了
Yes, it should work.
很好，這主意可行
It's a good distance from the water as well.
正好也夠靠近水邊
S-Slime!
史萊姆！
We should burn all monsters!
看我把這些魔物全燒光！
N-No!
不可以！
What did you do that for?
你做什麼啦？
It won't venture into a sunlit area.
史萊姆是不會到陽光下的
Slimes break down bat droppings and convert them into magic.
史萊姆會分解蝙蝠糞便 使其轉變成魔力
Without them, the dungeon will wither away.
如果沒有史萊姆 整座迷宮就會毫無生氣
Bats...
蝙蝠
Here.
給你
It's good.
好好吃喔
If they taste this good, I'm sure other animals eat them, too.
既然這麼美味 應該也會有其他動物吃它吧
I wonder what the bats here eat.
這裡的蝙蝠不曉得都會吃些什麼
When do these raspberries bear fruit?
這些木莓什麼時候會結果？
What animals feed on them?
會有什麼動物來吃它？
Without knowing that, I won't be able to design a dungeon.
如果不知道這些，就建造不了迷宮
There's so much I don't know.
我要學的事還很多呢
Thanks for bringing me here.
謝謝你帶我過來
I thought all I had to do was study magic to improve.
我一直以為只要專心學習魔法 自然就會變厲害
But it seems like I was mistaken.
不過我好像錯了
By the way, um...
話說回來，那個…
I'm Falin. What's your name?
我是法琳，你叫什麼名字？
I'm Marcille.
我是瑪露希爾
Falin, I'd love to be friends with you.
法琳，我想和你做朋友
The most brilliant female student in the school's history?
你最好會是學校有史以來 最優秀的才女啦
That's gotta be false.
別騙我了
It's true!
真的是啦！
Back in school, I was a top-notch student, you know!
我在學校的時候是模範生耶！
Anyway, this dungeon is a mind-boggling place.
總之這座迷宮是個不得了的地方
It's calculated to a tee,
經過了無數次的計算
and continuously circulates enormous amounts of magic.
讓龐大的魔力在迷宮裡不斷循環
If this lunatic magician really exists,
如果狂亂魔術師真的存在
he's definitely far from being sane.
我敢說那號人物肯定不尋常
Senshi, it would be best for you to find another place to live.
先西，為了你的安全著想 最好還是不要在這裡定居
That's none of your concern.
不用你多管閒事
In the first place, you hate magic,
到頭來，你雖然說討厭魔法
but this dungeon itself is constructed from magic!
但迷宮本身就是魔法的產物啊！
I can't hear you.
老夫聽不到
I see.
這樣啊
So she was talking about you.
原來她提到的就是你啊
When my sister had just enrolled in magic school,
我妹妹剛進魔法學校時所寫的信
her letters to me were full of worry.
上頭總是寫滿了她的不安
But ever since she told me that she had made a friend,
但自從某天她在信裡 報告她交到了朋友
it seemed like she was enjoying every day.
之後每天好像都過得很開心
She said you were an amazing person.
她在信中說你很了不起
She was always complimenting you.
時常都在誇你呢
She complimented you, too.
她也有誇你喔
She said she respected you.
說你是她很尊敬的人
Did she, now?
這樣啊
What's he good at?
他哪裡厲害啊？
He's really good at imitating a dog.
他模仿狗時學得很像
Oh, well, I guess this isn't the time to be whining.
算了，現在也不是閒聊這些的時候
All right.
好
Let's go and rescue Falin as soon as we can!
我們得快點去救法琳才行！
Come on!
快點…
If you're awake, get up already!
既然你都醒了，就快點起來！
Here's where we are now.
這是我們現在的位置
And this is the place the orcs mentioned where the Red Dragon was spotted.
半獸人告訴我們的 炎龍出沒位置則在這裡
It should take us about two days to get there.
應該兩天就走得到了
The dragon probably won't stay in one place,
炎龍八成不會乖乖待在原地不動
but it's not the sort of monster that roams around, either.
但應該也不是會到處亂跑的那種魔物
Ideally, we'll set up camp only two times more.
可以的話，我們頂多再紮營兩次
Once at the halfway point
一次在中間點
and then again just before we reach the Red Dragon.
一次在炎龍附近
We'll kick Laios out of bed when the candle burns out.
等到蠟燭熄了，我們就把萊歐斯打醒
Make sure to be ready.
有事要做就趁現在
Our next break is going to be a little way off.
距離下一次休息還要走一段路喔
I want to wipe myself down.
我想擦身體
Where?
在哪裡擦？
I'll do it in the corner of the room.
我會去房間角落擦的
Be quick about it.
麻煩快點
We'll be waiting outside.
那我們先去外面等
You can stay here.
你們可以待著沒關係啊
I can do it clothed, you know.
我可以穿著衣服擦
If you say so.
是喔
I'm bothering them, aren't I?
他們好像是在顧慮我
Maybe I should've studied illusion magic.
是不是該學些幻術魔法才對？
But that's not the issue, is it?
不過問題不在那裡吧
It was easier when half of us were girls.
之前隊伍內的男女人數各半 所以輕鬆多了
This is where we part.
我們要在這裡跟你們分開
What? Do you really have to leave now?
怎麼這樣？非得挑現在不可嗎？
We still don't know what happened to Falin.
我們還不知道法琳的下落
Sorry, but we have to make a living, too.
抱歉，我們也有自己的生活要顧
Just thinking about it is making me upset.
一回想起來，火氣就上來了
And I thought they were our friends!
虧我還當他們是夥伴！
Get up, Laios!
該起來了，萊歐斯！
Hey, wake up!
嘿，我叫你起來！
It's time to go!
我們要走了！
There.
好了
Oops. I boiled too much water.
糟糕，煮太久了
U...
水…
Undine!
水元素！
What is it?
怎麼回事？
My staff!
我的魔杖！
My Water-Walk...
我的水上步行…
The water is moving.
水擅自在動
You can't use weapons! We need fire.
你不能用武器！要有火才行
Fire?
火？
I could start a fire.
要點火嗎？
Marcille, do something on your own!
瑪露希爾，你自己想辦法吧！
Easier said than done.
就算你那麼說…
I hope I can hit it.
希望能打中
Marcille, don't just stand there!
瑪露希爾，你在發什麼呆啊？
Stay away from the water!
不要靠近水邊！
Your Water-Walk effects have worn off!
水上步行已經失效了！
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
This is bad! Keep moving!
不妙！別停下腳步！
I can't get away from it with this leg.
我的腳傷成這樣，逃不了多遠
Where is it hiding?
到底躲在哪裡？
She's moving so slowly. I can't bear to watch!
動作有夠遲鈍，我看不下去了！
Just give me a moment to start a fire!
再等一下，老夫現在就生火！
It won't be ready in time...
恐怕來不及
I'm running low on magic.
已經沒剩多少魔力了
I have to make my next attack count.
我得用這次的攻擊解決對方才行
Where is it?
在哪裡？
There must be some sort of sign.
有沒有什麼變化？
There!
找到了！
It's colored with blood.
血讓水元素變色了
It's so fast.
好快啊
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
Hey.
你看
It's...
那個是…
There's only one thing to do.
現在只有一條路可選
Run!
逃啊！
Marcille, how are you doing?
瑪露希爾，你的傷還好嗎？
I stopped the bleeding, but I'm low on blood and magic.
已經止血了，可是血液和魔力都不夠
I can't make a full recovery.
沒辦法完全治好
Sorry.
對不起
Don't be.
別道歉
Rest for a bit.
你先躺一下吧
Yeah.
好
I should've paid more attention to Falin's healing magic lessons.
早知道就認真點跟法琳學治療魔法了
Hey, Laios.
我說啊，萊歐斯
What do we do now?
接下來要怎麼辦？
We can't continue on with a mage out of magic.
我們沒辦法帶著 魔力耗盡的魔術師走下去
And we can't move forward without Water-Walk either.
而且現在沒了水上步行 我們哪裡都去不了
Let's wait for other adventurers to come by.
我們等其他冒險者經過吧
One of them might be a healer or a mage.
希望能遇到治療師或魔術師
You really think a helpful adventurer will just happen to show up?
最好是剛好會有那種 熱心助人的冒險者經過啦
We don't even have anything to offer in return anyway.
我們手上沒有半點東西可以交換啊
The only thing we have is Kelpie meat.
頂多也只有水棲馬的肉而已
Better hope our adventurer is starving, then.
只好指望對方餓得快死了
This source of nutrition is a precious rarity in this dungeon.
在迷宮裡，這類營養成分稀少 是很珍貴的喔
That's beside the point!
現在沒有在討論營養啦！
Meat.
肉
Do you have its liver as well?
裡面是不是也有肝臟？
Of course.
當然有
After all, the liver is rich in iron.
肝臟可是富含鐵質啊
Iron...
鐵質…
This means...
讓人聯想到…
-A barbecue!
-烤肉！
Mane, neck, liver,
頭上的水草、頸肉、肝臟
ribs, tail, round, loin,
五花肉、尾肉、腿肉、里脊肉
and vegetables.
還有蔬菜
KELPIE GRILLED MEAT
（水棲馬烤肉）
Marcille.
瑪露希爾
Can you sit up?
起得來嗎？
We prepared something nice for you.
我們替你準備了好東西
Round meat.
腿肉
What about the liver?
肝烤好了嗎？
The guts should be cooked thoroughly.
內臟要煮到熟透才可以
Sorry, Marcille. I'll be eating first.
抱歉，瑪露希爾，我先吃了
It's not so gamey.
沒有什麼腥味
Yeah, it's a bit stringy, but it's good.
是啊，筋有點多，不過滿好吃的
Does it taste more like a horse or a marine animal?
到底是比較接近馬肉 還是海獸的味道呢？
It's too bad I haven't had the chance to try either, so I can't say.
可惜我兩種都沒吃過，無從判斷
Rib meat.
五花肉
The fat tastes sweet.
油脂好甜
It's so soft.
好軟喔
Marcille, the liver is done.
瑪露希爾，肝熟了喔
Tenderloin meat.
腰內肉
It melts in your mouth.
就像在嘴裡融化一樣
I love this.
我喜歡這個
More liver for you, Marcille.
再給你多一點的肝，瑪露希爾
Tail meat.
尾肉
It's good.
好吃耶
It tastes pretty interesting.
味道真是不可思議
Have more, Marcille.
拿去，瑪露希爾
More liver, Marcille.
該吃肝了，瑪露希爾
Is it good, Marcille?
好吃嗎？瑪露希爾
Eat up, Marcille.
多吃點，瑪露希爾
How do you like it, Marcille?
喜歡嗎？瑪露希爾
Let me eat the other parts, too!
也給我吃其他部位的肉啦！
Looks like she's regained some energy.
看來她稍微有點精神了
Liver sure is potent.
肝臟之力真厲害
But what are we going to do about her magic shortage?
先不管這點，魔力不足該怎麼解決？
If only there was a meat that could replenish magic.
如果有可以恢復魔力的肉就好了
Why did you stuff magic grass in a Basilisk?
你為什麼要把魔力草 塞進巴西利斯克裡面啦？
I believe it was the best choice.
老夫認為那是最好的選擇
Is it just me, or do you also smell something?
你們有沒有聞到什麼味道？
It's coming from below.
從下面傳上來的
What is that smell?
是什麼味道？
Is it the scent of grilling meat?
肉烤熟的味道吧？
Someone must be cooking.
好像是有人在下廚
What, seriously?
真是的，搞什麼啊？
What kind of fool
到底是哪個蠢蛋
cooks meat in a place like this?
偏偏在這種鬼地方烤肉？
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：江俊諺